so U
Janna is referred
to as a sense of
safety in what way is it safety and what
is it safe
from is it possible to point out some
type of or more mundane or lower level
safety that carries the same principle
as a safety of J which could therefore
help to lead one in the right direction
for developing it so what is the sense
of
safety so it's
safety from your own mind being able to
turn against
you it's basically safety from within
you know like all those sutas with the
simile of an intimate friend working
against you trying to kill you in your
sleep and stuff like that well that's
your own mind
so Janna is the beginning of
safety from your own mind where you know
it and that's why you feel that Rapture
or whatever they want to translate it
pity like you you feel if like a
physical relief Joy
upliftment whichever way you want to
describe that
pleasure for the first time you're
feeling safe safe
from the
most accurate most precise root of
suffering which is your mind affected
with craving and you and you see that that is
craving and you and you see that that is
impossible mind cannot possibly turn in
that direction in Janna and on account
of that to experience confidence and
immeasurable safety
safety
so the mundane examples well I mean the
Buddha gave number of mundane examples
and you could see why they would they
would translate quite
well uh yes say say like the the example of
uh yes say say like the the example of
being released from a
prison that was the example for the
pleasure of the first JRE so imagine you
in prison falsely or rightly doesn't
matter um and you worry about your
property about your house about your
wealth about your family about
everything everything you worked
for and then you You released from that
prison so you are still apprehensive to
see what you're going to find and then
you go you get back home and things are
even better than what you left how you
left them so you have a tremendous
release and joy and happiness that not
just it did not it was not taken or lost
it got even better so that relief
basically it's the same like um say you
feel imprisoned by the possibility of
your own
mind to disobey you to go against itself
on that most fundamental level so like
you can't prevent things you can't
prevent perception from arising you
can't prevent feelings from arising and
you know that and that's not the problem
the problem and the the fearful part the
the the anxious part is the fact that
you could end up perceiving something
suddenly or feeling something suddenly
and your mind will decide to turn
against it internally to turn against
itself perceiving
it and that's like the deepest sort of
pain denial
anguish so whatever specific thing that
might be it will have to fall into this
category it will have to have a Common
Thread of a mind
turning against itself when paired with
something that's
deemed unwanted unpleasant whatever and
see that's the everpresent sort of
possibility not the fact that you can
perceive something upsetting but the
fact that upon perceiving something
petting upsetting your mind can
really um turn against
you and that will show you the
full extent of your impotence and an
imprisonment your imprisoned under your
own mind under that wild animal that we
often refer to it's all fine and good
when it doesn't turn against you and
then you pretend it never
will but at the back of your mind you
are aware that there is always a
possibility that something would disturb
that mind to such an extent that it
would want to cancel you as well
it will want to cancel everything and
you will have no say in
it so that's why people go around
fearing this or that or
avoiding because they don't want to
experience the the the ress of that mind
if it's upset they don't want to upset
it that's why people don't want to keep
the precepts and and sensory strength
because that already starts upsetting
the mind that then starts throwing all
sorts of irrational things at you and
fears and doubts and hindrances
just to to to to show its power
basically to get you back in
line and none of that's possible in the
first J in the first J the roles are
completely reversed you are fully withdrawn from
reversed you are fully withdrawn from
the entire extent and power of that mind
and you know it and the mind knows it
and that's why it Cales
down it was like the example you guys
the other day about the tamed elephant
now the M you know and the mind knows
that it's free anyway yeah that it's
tame that is calm the craving is gone so
now it's like I I cannot crave anymore
the Mind knows it yeah like once you
tame the Mind properly then exactly even
that mind will realize oh actually th
this is better for for me
too like the only reason he was doing
what he was
doing was because he was wild and
untamed and he didn't know anything
better than
that but once you sort of honed it in
trained it calmed it tamed
it uh made it
incapable of turning against you against
itself then he realiz oh this was
actually for my welfare all all along I
just wasn't aware of
it keeping the precepts was pleasant
sense restrain was pure joy
but until you develop that tameness of
that mind it will feel like the
opposite because the mind will resist it
so once it tastes the pleasure of being
uh having fulfilled the precepts yeah
taste the pleasure of sense restraint
that's already like that getting it
ready to realize that well that's why
like for for a householder in the sutas
you know the Buddha did not teach them
meditation techniques and whatnot he
told them to to reflect and frequently
recollect their unbroken virtue their
aggregated of virtue their faith in the
Buddha the dharm the S the dhama uh
basically recollect those things think
about those things and the mind will
come down and experience Pleasant
abiding here and now which is a
description for J when he came to
monks Pleasant abiding Here and Now AIDS
in the Turning complete Turning Away of
from all UNH wholesome things yes
exactly it goes in the same direction
that's that's the result
Yeah the more pleasure you get get from
virtue the more it's going to go the
more you realize oh this is blameless
easy blameless easy and effortless yeah
no Jana is the result of rightly taming
your mind